this is a video about history and
this is a video about history and technology and culture all colliding in
technology and culture all colliding in
technology and culture all colliding in the fascinating vessel of little tiny
the fascinating vessel of little tiny
the fascinating vessel of little tiny choo choo trains we're going to take a
choo choo trains we're going to take a
choo choo trains we're going to take a look at and play with this stuff some
look at and play with this stuff some
look at and play with this stuff some extremely unique sound generators and
extremely unique sound generators and
extremely unique sound generators and synthesizers from the late 1960s that
synthesizers from the late 1960s that
synthesizers from the late 1960s that delivered audio signals on the electric
delivered audio signals on the electric
delivered audio signals on the electric line used to propel model trains so if
line used to propel model trains so if
line used to propel model trains so if you had thousands of dollars to spare 40
you had thousands of dollars to spare 40
you had thousands of dollars to spare 40 years ago you could make your model
years ago you could make your model
years ago you could make your model train sound like this
train sound like this
train sound like this and yeah that's probably a little bit
and yeah that's probably a little bit
and yeah that's probably a little bit underwhelming if you're used to hearing
underwhelming if you're used to hearing
underwhelming if you're used to hearing stuff like this which is why I popped
stuff like this which is why I popped
stuff like this which is why I popped open a bottle of whiskey and soldered
open a bottle of whiskey and soldered
open a bottle of whiskey and soldered theck out of this stuff so we could get
theck out of this stuff so we could get
theck out of this stuff so we could get sounds that sound a little bit more like
sounds that sound a little bit more like
sounds that sound a little bit more like this well then all aboard hold on to
this well then all aboard hold on to
this well then all aboard hold on to your what do you call the seat that a
your what do you call the seat that a
your what do you call the seat that a train engineer or conductor sits in hold
train engineer or conductor sits in hold
train engineer or conductor sits in hold on to your
a-103 certified power rail locomotive
a-103 certified power rail locomotive seats
seats
seats [Music]
[Music]
[Music] okay so let's go back to the year
okay so let's go back to the year
okay so let's go back to the year 1965 probably if you're familiar with
1965 probably if you're familiar with
1965 probably if you're familiar with this channel then you probably know that
this channel then you probably know that
this channel then you probably know that I get really obsessive with research and
I get really obsessive with research and
I get really obsessive with research and believe it or not this video was
believe it or not this video was
believe it or not this video was actually really difficult to research
actually really difficult to research
actually really difficult to research mostly because everybody involved with
mostly because everybody involved with
mostly because everybody involved with the creation of these original devices
the creation of these original devices
the creation of these original devices is dead which is kind of spooky and
is dead which is kind of spooky and
is dead which is kind of spooky and convenient now that I think think about
convenient now that I think think about
convenient now that I think think about it all right so the year is probably
it all right so the year is probably
it all right so the year is probably 1965 and a prominent IBM engineer named
1965 and a prominent IBM engineer named
1965 and a prominent IBM engineer named Robert long Necker AKA chooo Bob long
Robert long Necker AKA chooo Bob long
Robert long Necker AKA chooo Bob long Necker I am trying to make a serious
Necker I am trying to make a serious
Necker I am trying to make a serious film about train syn get out it would be
film about train syn get out it would be
film about train syn get out it would be safe to assume that this nickname was
safe to assume that this nickname was
safe to assume that this nickname was derived from his interest and maybe even
derived from his interest and maybe even
derived from his interest and maybe even obsession with model trains Bob decided
obsession with model trains Bob decided
obsession with model trains Bob decided to take a break from inventing dram or
to take a break from inventing dram or
to take a break from inventing dram or whatever IBM was doing at the time and
whatever IBM was doing at the time and
whatever IBM was doing at the time and instead um make model trains sound like
instead um make model trains sound like
instead um make model trains sound like real trains and I can't figure out the
real trains and I can't figure out the
real trains and I can't figure out the exact timeline but over the the next few
exact timeline but over the the next few
exact timeline but over the the next few years Bob worked with a company called
years Bob worked with a company called
years Bob worked with a company called pfm or Pacific FastMail to do just that
pfm or Pacific FastMail to do just that
pfm or Pacific FastMail to do just that it is worth noting that synthesizers
it is worth noting that synthesizers
it is worth noting that synthesizers weren't exactly popular and were pretty
weren't exactly popular and were pretty
weren't exactly popular and were pretty obscure when Bob was first developing
obscure when Bob was first developing
obscure when Bob was first developing this stuff and on the other side of the
this stuff and on the other side of the
this stuff and on the other side of the country another Bob was designing what
country another Bob was designing what
country another Bob was designing what would become the first Moog synthesizers
would become the first Moog synthesizers
would become the first Moog synthesizers but the main pfm sound system wasn't
but the main pfm sound system wasn't
but the main pfm sound system wasn't just a sound system it was a clever
just a sound system it was a clever
just a sound system it was a clever redesign of the master Drive controller
redesign of the master Drive controller
redesign of the master Drive controller for a model train set inside this type
for a model train set inside this type
for a model train set inside this type of model train there's a tender Drive
of model train there's a tender Drive
of model train there's a tender Drive which picks up electric power that's
which picks up electric power that's
which picks up electric power that's just distributed through the tracks and
just distributed through the tracks and
just distributed through the tracks and it keeps the train moving without
it keeps the train moving without
it keeps the train moving without needing any wires connected or internal
needing any wires connected or internal
needing any wires connected or internal battery this controller allowed you to
battery this controller allowed you to
battery this controller allowed you to not only increase the power to the
not only increase the power to the
not only increase the power to the tender drive but it would synthesize
tender drive but it would synthesize
tender drive but it would synthesize audio in sync with the amount of power
audio in sync with the amount of power
audio in sync with the amount of power that you were sending and then
that you were sending and then
that you were sending and then incredibly it would convert AC to DC and
incredibly it would convert AC to DC and
incredibly it would convert AC to DC and send audio over the DC power line to the
send audio over the DC power line to the
send audio over the DC power line to the train which would then be played from a
train which would then be played from a
train which would then be played from a small speaker that would be installed
small speaker that would be installed
small speaker that would be installed inside the model train and traveling
inside the model train and traveling
inside the model train and traveling around the tracks with it that's pretty
around the tracks with it that's pretty
around the tracks with it that's pretty cool then there's the quadr tape unit
cool then there's the quadr tape unit
cool then there's the quadr tape unit which I'm not sure why it's called quadr
which I'm not sure why it's called quadr
which I'm not sure why it's called quadr tape because there's three tape decks
tape because there's three tape decks
tape because there's three tape decks but apparently you can piggyback three
but apparently you can piggyback three
but apparently you can piggyback three of these and have nine total tape Loops
of these and have nine total tape Loops
of these and have nine total tape Loops going to reproduce virtually any sound
going to reproduce virtually any sound
going to reproduce virtually any sound that you could think of coming out of a
that you could think of coming out of a
that you could think of coming out of a real train it's been really hard to
real train it's been really hard to
real train it's been really hard to verify what the original pricing was but
verify what the original pricing was but
verify what the original pricing was but I believe that the pfm Mark I had
I believe that the pfm Mark I had
I believe that the pfm Mark I had originally retailed for $1,500 which was
originally retailed for $1,500 which was
originally retailed for $1,500 which was like the cost of a Volkswagen at the
like the cost of a Volkswagen at the
like the cost of a Volkswagen at the time when you adjust that for inflation
time when you adjust that for inflation
time when you adjust that for inflation that's like 12 or $133,000 so it it
that's like 12 or $133,000 so it it
that's like 12 or $133,000 so it it would be reasonable to assume that
would be reasonable to assume that
would be reasonable to assume that anybody who owned this at the time was
anybody who owned this at the time was
anybody who owned this at the time was not hungry I simply cannot find any
not hungry I simply cannot find any
not hungry I simply cannot find any information that tells me how much the
information that tells me how much the
information that tells me how much the quadr tape or the smaller synthesizer
quadr tape or the smaller synthesizer
quadr tape or the smaller synthesizer unit cost or retailed for when they were
unit cost or retailed for when they were
unit cost or retailed for when they were first released but it seems like they
first released but it seems like they
first released but it seems like they weren't selling well and they had some
weren't selling well and they had some
weren't selling well and they had some Overstock because they were liquidated
Overstock because they were liquidated
Overstock because they were liquidated for quite a lot less in a catalog that
for quite a lot less in a catalog that
for quite a lot less in a catalog that came out in like the mid '70s
came out in like the mid '70s
came out in like the mid '70s unfortunately Choo Chu Bob died of lung
unfortunately Choo Chu Bob died of lung
unfortunately Choo Chu Bob died of lung cancer in 2004 and when I was trying to
cancer in 2004 and when I was trying to
cancer in 2004 and when I was trying to piece this historical puzzle together I
piece this historical puzzle together I
piece this historical puzzle together I started stalking some of his surviving
started stalking some of his surviving
started stalking some of his surviving family members to see if I could find
family members to see if I could find
family members to see if I could find any information or photos and believe it
any information or photos and believe it
any information or photos and believe it or not his grandson is popular train and
or not his grandson is popular train and
or not his grandson is popular train and sometimes music YouTuber Heist my
sometimes music YouTuber Heist my
sometimes music YouTuber Heist my granddad made the first model train
granddad made the first model train
granddad made the first model train sound systems Heist actually made a
sound systems Heist actually made a
sound systems Heist actually made a video about another Train sound machine
video about another Train sound machine
video about another Train sound machine his grandfather made later on the pbl
his grandfather made later on the pbl
his grandfather made later on the pbl foreground sound system which was an
foreground sound system which was an
foreground sound system which was an improvement for the train stuff itself
improvement for the train stuff itself
improvement for the train stuff itself and has its own interesting features
and has its own interesting features
and has its own interesting features which you can watch in heist's video
which you can watch in heist's video
which you can watch in heist's video which I'll link below but since it seems
which I'll link below but since it seems
which I'll link below but since it seems to be mostly digital it's probably not
to be mostly digital it's probably not
to be mostly digital it's probably not going to be as is appealing for mouth
going to be as is appealing for mouth
going to be as is appealing for mouth breathers like myself and my viewers so
breathers like myself and my viewers so
breathers like myself and my viewers so yeah you want to check it out with me
yeah you want to check it out with me
yeah you want to check it out with me come
come
come [Music]
[Music]
[Music] on in the
begin I'll show you the innards of this
begin I'll show you the innards of this after my little demonstration here
after my little demonstration here
after my little demonstration here because I'm so scared that if I just
because I'm so scared that if I just
because I'm so scared that if I just lift this up again something might
lift this up again something might
lift this up again something might become disjointed and then uh we'll be
become disjointed and then uh we'll be
become disjointed and then uh we'll be done the thing just makes insane noise
done the thing just makes insane noise
done the thing just makes insane noise on its
[Music]
[Music] own it's turned away up when I'm doing
own it's turned away up when I'm doing
own it's turned away up when I'm doing that that's coming from the Doppler
that that's coming from the Doppler
that that's coming from the Doppler effect from the exhaust so let's turn
effect from the exhaust so let's turn
effect from the exhaust so let's turn that all the way down turn the exhaust
that all the way down turn the exhaust
that all the way down turn the exhaust up we have cut
up we have cut
up we have cut off we have
off we have
off we have tone volume and then Doppler
is pretty
is pretty cool and then there's a resonance
Peak then there's a
Peak then there's a generator which is like the most awful
generator which is like the most awful
generator which is like the most awful sound that this thing makes I think then
sound that this thing makes I think then
sound that this thing makes I think then we have a blower and coupling and I
we have a blower and coupling and I
we have a blower and coupling and I believe that those are are coming in
believe that those are are coming in
believe that those are are coming in from tapes that I don't have hooked up
from tapes that I don't have hooked up
from tapes that I don't have hooked up but here's wheel noise I don't have
but here's wheel noise I don't have
but here's wheel noise I don't have wheel noise on the tape I actually just
wheel noise on the tape I actually just
wheel noise on the tape I actually just have some Ambience from
outside this side of the tape is a
outside this side of the tape is a little more screwed up this is the
[Music]
[Music] Bell I'm assuming that everything up
Bell I'm assuming that everything up
Bell I'm assuming that everything up here in this area is just tape controls
here in this area is just tape controls
here in this area is just tape controls cuz you can have up to three of these
cuz you can have up to three of these
cuz you can have up to three of these machines for nine total tape AP if
machines for nine total tape AP if
machines for nine total tape AP if you're a psychopath we could output to
you're a psychopath we could output to
you're a psychopath we could output to Echo and Reverb which I found some old
Echo and Reverb which I found some old
Echo and Reverb which I found some old cave drawings of how that works I'm not
cave drawings of how that works I'm not
cave drawings of how that works I'm not really sure how echko fits into this at
really sure how echko fits into this at
really sure how echko fits into this at all the Reverb is under here and I'll
all the Reverb is under here and I'll
all the Reverb is under here and I'll show you that at the end of this that
show you that at the end of this that
show you that at the end of this that it's a spring reverb unit that I plan to
it's a spring reverb unit that I plan to
it's a spring reverb unit that I plan to use for other things cuz it has standard
use for other things cuz it has standard
use for other things cuz it has standard RCA in and out the way that I have all
RCA in and out the way that I have all
RCA in and out the way that I have all of this hooked up it would have just
of this hooked up it would have just
of this hooked up it would have just made things more complicated and noisy
made things more complicated and noisy
made things more complicated and noisy so I just opted out of it for now
so I just opted out of it for now
so I just opted out of it for now throttle and Direction and acceleration
throttle and Direction and acceleration
throttle and Direction and acceleration and de acceleration will do nothing
and de acceleration will do nothing
and de acceleration will do nothing because that's being filtered out in a
because that's being filtered out in a
because that's being filtered out in a little Transformer that I made here so
little Transformer that I made here so
little Transformer that I made here so I'm not sending lots of electricity to
I'm not sending lots of electricity to
I'm not sending lots of electricity to my mixer and then we have
my mixer and then we have
my mixer and then we have hiss and a different type of hiss if you
hiss and a different type of hiss if you
hiss and a different type of hiss if you like your hisses a nice white noise
party now for my favorite part this has
party now for my favorite part this has a highly customizable whistle and I've
a highly customizable whistle and I've
a highly customizable whistle and I've disabled this potentiometer because I
disabled this potentiometer because I
disabled this potentiometer because I wanted this whistle to go to an external
wanted this whistle to go to an external
wanted this whistle to go to an external output so I could play with
output so I could play with
output so I could play with it and this basically changes the pitch
it and this basically changes the pitch
it and this basically changes the pitch of the overall
of the overall
[Music]
[Music] whistle so this is five different tone
[Music] generators I'm becoming quite a pro at
this okay so moving on to the older and
this okay so moving on to the older and less complicated crazy one there's no
less complicated crazy one there's no
less complicated crazy one there's no tapes in here there is a bell sound but
tapes in here there is a bell sound but
tapes in here there is a bell sound but it's an analog tone
it's an analog tone
it's an analog tone [Music]
noise again the throttle and Direction
noise again the throttle and Direction those aren't audio generators that's
those aren't audio generators that's
those aren't audio generators that's just power going to the tracks and I
just power going to the tracks and I
just power going to the tracks and I filtered that out here we
filtered that out here we
filtered that out here we [Applause]
[Applause]
[Applause] go the whistle generator on this one's
go the whistle generator on this one's
go the whistle generator on this one's simpler but still
simpler but still
simpler but still [Applause]
[Applause]
[Applause] [Music]
[Music]
[Music] fun all right let's verb it up
[Music] [Applause]
[Applause]
[Applause] [Music]
[Music]
[Music] okay e
[Music] [Laughter]
we have a spring reverb and it's mono
we have a spring reverb and it's mono but you could see the spr well let me
but you could see the spr well let me
but you could see the spr well let me use this camera I think I'm going to
use this camera I think I'm going to
use this camera I think I'm going to keep this actually let's open it up real
keep this actually let's open it up real
keep this actually let's open it up real fast I'm going to need a bigger tool
fast I'm going to need a bigger tool
fast I'm going to need a bigger tool that's what she said there you
that's what she said there you
that's what she said there you go so that's the front of
go so that's the front of
go so that's the front of it pop this off
it pop this off
it pop this off so I cleaned this up really good and
so I cleaned this up really good and
so I cleaned this up really good and soldered some of the joints from the
soldered some of the joints from the
soldered some of the joints from the synthesizer parts to go out to here and
synthesizer parts to go out to here and
synthesizer parts to go out to here and then this could easily be expanded on
then this could easily be expanded on
then this could easily be expanded on with something like this maybe something
with something like this maybe something
with something like this maybe something that actually fits it and then that
that actually fits it and then that
that actually fits it and then that could go to a breadboard and then audio
could go to a breadboard and then audio
could go to a breadboard and then audio out and so on when I first opened this
out and so on when I first opened this
out and so on when I first opened this up I saw these capacitors and was like
up I saw these capacitors and was like
up I saw these capacitors and was like nope absolutely not not touching this at
nope absolutely not not touching this at
nope absolutely not not touching this at all and then I looked at the actual
all and then I looked at the actual
all and then I looked at the actual rating of them and it's 35 volts and
rating of them and it's 35 volts and
rating of them and it's 35 volts and 4700 microfarads which is not that crazy
4700 microfarads which is not that crazy
4700 microfarads which is not that crazy I love things like this because it's
I love things like this because it's
I love things like this because it's such a good Testament to how much more
such a good Testament to how much more
such a good Testament to how much more efficient electronics are now a
efficient electronics are now a
efficient electronics are now a capacitor with similar specs now would
capacitor with similar specs now would
capacitor with similar specs now would be like maybe that big by the way if
be like maybe that big by the way if
be like maybe that big by the way if you're not into electronics and you
you're not into electronics and you
you're not into electronics and you don't know or care what a capacitor is
don't know or care what a capacitor is
don't know or care what a capacitor is this information is really important if
this information is really important if
this information is really important if you ever open something up and you see
you ever open something up and you see
you ever open something up and you see things that look like this they store
things that look like this they store
things that look like this they store electricity and they can be dangerous if
electricity and they can be dangerous if
electricity and they can be dangerous if you see a capacitor this size on
you see a capacitor this size on
you see a capacitor this size on something that's made after I don't know
something that's made after I don't know
something that's made after I don't know the year 2000 or so probably in HVAC or
the year 2000 or so probably in HVAC or
the year 2000 or so probably in HVAC or something like that is where you would
something like that is where you would
something like that is where you would see those and if you touch it when it's
see those and if you touch it when it's
see those and if you touch it when it's charged you will meet your maker now of
charged you will meet your maker now of
charged you will meet your maker now of course you can manually discharge them
course you can manually discharge them
course you can manually discharge them and that still can be dangerous and I've
and that still can be dangerous and I've
and that still can be dangerous and I've gotten shocked a whole bunch of times
gotten shocked a whole bunch of times
gotten shocked a whole bunch of times doing it I would just say don't touch
doing it I would just say don't touch
doing it I would just say don't touch these unless you know what you're doing
these unless you know what you're doing
these unless you know what you're doing so the quadr tape inputs are serial
so the quadr tape inputs are serial
so the quadr tape inputs are serial ports by the way these are not XLR
ports by the way these are not XLR
ports by the way these are not XLR adapters covered up by something there
adapters covered up by something there
adapters covered up by something there for power when I first saw this unit
for power when I first saw this unit
for power when I first saw this unit online I thought that you'd be able to
online I thought that you'd be able to
online I thought that you'd be able to just get the audio from the Reverb
just get the audio from the Reverb
just get the audio from the Reverb outputs you cannot unfortunately there's
outputs you cannot unfortunately there's
outputs you cannot unfortunately there's another output over here that's not
another output over here that's not
another output over here that's not really covered in the documentation and
really covered in the documentation and
really covered in the documentation and it seems like these outputs only work
it seems like these outputs only work
it seems like these outputs only work when you have a proper amount of power
when you have a proper amount of power
when you have a proper amount of power coming out and back into the unit from
coming out and back into the unit from
coming out and back into the unit from the tracks it's basically I don't I
the tracks it's basically I don't I
the tracks it's basically I don't I don't really know why it does that it
don't really know why it does that it
don't really know why it does that it wouldn't be a safety thing if anything
wouldn't be a safety thing if anything
wouldn't be a safety thing if anything it would make it less safe speaking of
it would make it less safe speaking of
it would make it less safe speaking of safety while messing around with
safety while messing around with
safety while messing around with electronics especially outside of the
electronics especially outside of the
electronics especially outside of the case I was happy to see that there's a
case I was happy to see that there's a
case I was happy to see that there's a fuse and a reset button all right it's a
fuse and a reset button all right it's a
fuse and a reset button all right it's a quadr tape and we have a fuse back here
quadr tape and we have a fuse back here
quadr tape and we have a fuse back here as well I got them all working this one
as well I got them all working this one
as well I got them all working this one was honestly the worst but check this
was honestly the worst but check this
was honestly the worst but check this out boom this one is the older of the
out boom this one is the older of the
out boom this one is the older of the bunch and it worked fine I didn't need
bunch and it worked fine I didn't need
bunch and it worked fine I didn't need to open it up for anything similar
to open it up for anything similar
to open it up for anything similar situation with the fuse and the reset
situation with the fuse and the reset
situation with the fuse and the reset switch and the outputs that have power
switch and the outputs that have power
switch and the outputs that have power that need to be filtered before you
that need to be filtered before you
that need to be filtered before you bring them into something every switch
bring them into something every switch
bring them into something every switch on this thing is super smooth probably
on this thing is super smooth probably
on this thing is super smooth probably smoother than anything you would buy
smoother than anything you would buy
smoother than anything you would buy today some of the potentiometers are a
today some of the potentiometers are a
today some of the potentiometers are a little sticky meaning that they sound a
little sticky meaning that they sound a
little sticky meaning that they sound a little bit crackly when you turn them
little bit crackly when you turn them
little bit crackly when you turn them but that usually be fixed with a Q-tip
but that usually be fixed with a Q-tip
but that usually be fixed with a Q-tip and some rubbing alcohol I guess I'm
and some rubbing alcohol I guess I'm
and some rubbing alcohol I guess I'm just always happy to see something as
just always happy to see something as
just always happy to see something as old as I am that's not as up by
old as I am that's not as up by
old as I am that's not as up by time as I am was fun I reached out to
time as I am was fun I reached out to
time as I am was fun I reached out to Heist to see if he wanted me to send
Heist to see if he wanted me to send
Heist to see if he wanted me to send this stuff to him CU it is his
this stuff to him CU it is his
this stuff to him CU it is his grandfather's Legacy after all but
grandfather's Legacy after all but
grandfather's Legacy after all but unsurprisingly he already has most of it
unsurprisingly he already has most of it
unsurprisingly he already has most of it and I really would like to see it go to
and I really would like to see it go to
and I really would like to see it go to good use because I'm so busy that it's
good use because I'm so busy that it's
good use because I'm so busy that it's probably just going to collect dust here
probably just going to collect dust here
probably just going to collect dust here so I reached out to some local model
so I reached out to some local model
so I reached out to some local model train and electrical engineering groups
train and electrical engineering groups
train and electrical engineering groups to see if anybody has any clever ideas
to see if anybody has any clever ideas
to see if anybody has any clever ideas for what they could do with it I was
for what they could do with it I was
for what they could do with it I was Vaguely Familiar with the model train
Vaguely Familiar with the model train
Vaguely Familiar with the model train sound generators years ago as more
sound generators years ago as more
sound generators years ago as more people seem to be into model trains
people seem to be into model trains
people seem to be into model trains years ago than they are now I I am not
years ago than they are now I I am not
years ago than they are now I I am not into model trains personally but I would
into model trains personally but I would
into model trains personally but I would like to thank Mikey 303 for sort of
like to thank Mikey 303 for sort of
like to thank Mikey 303 for sort of reintroducing me to this parallel
reintroducing me to this parallel
reintroducing me to this parallel universe of synthesizers I would also
universe of synthesizers I would also
universe of synthesizers I would also like to thank II for sending me kind of
like to thank II for sending me kind of
like to thank II for sending me kind of a little birthday bundle of these
a little birthday bundle of these
a little birthday bundle of these wireless headphones and the wireless
wireless headphones and the wireless
wireless headphones and the wireless monitors that are in the other room
monitors that are in the other room
monitors that are in the other room those are nice and of course I would
those are nice and of course I would
those are nice and of course I would like to thank my patreon members because
like to thank my patreon members because
like to thank my patreon members because this video would not be possible without
this video would not be possible without
this video would not be possible without you and if you want access to an amazing
you and if you want access to an amazing
you and if you want access to an amazing Community with monthly songw writing
Community with monthly songw writing
Community with monthly songw writing challenges and unreleased music and
challenges and unreleased music and
challenges and unreleased music and field recordings and audio assets then
field recordings and audio assets then
field recordings and audio assets then my patreon is for you and you can join
my patreon is for you and you can join
my patreon is for you and you can join for as little as $1 also one thing I'm
for as little as $1 also one thing I'm
for as little as $1 also one thing I'm going to have to point out for every
going to have to point out for every
going to have to point out for every single patreon call of action from now
single patreon call of action from now
single patreon call of action from now on is that if you are an Apple user
on is that if you are an Apple user
on is that if you are an Apple user using an iPhone or an iPad and you are
using an iPhone or an iPad and you are
using an iPhone or an iPad and you are using Apple pay or Apple's payment
using Apple pay or Apple's payment
using Apple pay or Apple's payment gateway to sign up for my patreon or
gateway to sign up for my patreon or
gateway to sign up for my patreon or anybody's patreon you will be charged an
anybody's patreon you will be charged an
anybody's patreon you will be charged an extra 30 or so% or your creator will get
extra 30 or so% or your creator will get
extra 30 or so% or your creator will get about 30% less there's an easy way
about 30% less there's an easy way
about 30% less there's an easy way around this just tie a little string
around this just tie a little string
around this just tie a little string around your finger to remind you to open
around your finger to remind you to open
around your finger to remind you to open up a web browser and pay with a normal
up a web browser and pay with a normal
up a web browser and pay with a normal credit card or PayPal or whatever else
credit card or PayPal or whatever else
credit card or PayPal or whatever else thanks for watching keep creating bye